CHAPTER 19 There is no use your telling me that you are going to be good,” cried Lord
Henry, dipping his white fingers into a red copper bowl filled with rose waterer
You are quite perfect. Pray, don’t change.” Dorian Gray shook his head. “No, Harry, I
have done too many dreadful things in my life I'm not going to do anymore I began
my good actions yesterday well were you yesterday?” “In the country, Harry. I was
staying at a little inn by myself.” “My dear boy,” said Lord Henry, smiling, “anybody
can be good in the country. There are no temptations there. That is the reason why
people who live out of town are so absolutely uncivilized. Civilization is not by any
means an easy thing to attain to. There are only two ways by which man can reach
it. One is by being cultured, the other by being corrupt. Country people have no
opportunity of being either, so they stagnate.” “Culture and corruption,” echoed
Dorian. “I have known something of both. It seems terrible to me now that they
should ever be found together. For I have a new ideal, Harry. I am going to
alter. I think I have altered.” “You have not yet told me what
your good action was. Or did you say you had done more than one?” asked his
companion as he spilled into his plate a little crimson pyramid of seeded
strawberries and, through a perforated, shell-shaped spoon, snowed white sugar upon
them. “I can tell you, Harry. It is not a story I could tell to anyone else. I
spared somebody. It sounds vain, but you understand what I mean. She was quite
beautiful and wonderfully like cibil vain I think it was that which first
attracted me to her. You remember cibil don’t you? How long ago that seems! Well
heti was not one of our own class, of course. She was simply a girl in a
village. But I really loved her I'm quite sure that I loved her. All during this
wonderful May that we've been having, I used to run down and see her two or
three times a week. Yesterday she met me in a little orchard. The apple blossoms kept tumbling
down on her hair, and she was laughing. We were to have gone away together this
morning at dawn. Suddenly I determined to leave her as flowerlike as I had found
her.” “I should think the novelty of the emotion must have given you a thrill of
real pleasure, Dorian,” interrupted Lord Henry. “But I can finish your idial for
you. You gave her good advice and broke her heart. That was the beginning of your
reformation.” “Harry, you are horrible! You mustn’t say these dreadful things heti's
heart is not broken. Of course, she cried and all that. But there is no disgrace
upon her. She can live, like perator in her garden of mint and
marold And weep over a faithless florisil said Lord Henry, laughing, as he
leaned back in his chair. “My dear Dorian, you have the most curiously boyish moods.
Do you think this girl will ever be really content now with any one of her
own rank? I suppose she will be married someday to a rough carter or a grinning
Plowman the fact of having met you, and loved you, will teach her to despise her
husband, and she will be wretched. From a moral point of you I cannot say that I
think much of your great renunciation. Even as a beginning, it is
poor. Besides, how do you know that heti isn’t floating at the present moment in
some Starlet Mill Pond with lovely water lies around her, like a
felia I can’t bear this, Harry! You mock at everything, and then suggest the most serious
tragedies. I am sorry I told you now. I
don’t care what you say to me. I know I was right in acting as I
did. Poor heti As I rode past the farm this morning, I saw her white face at the
window, like a spray of jasmine. Don’t let us talk about it anymore and don’t try
to persuade me that the first good action I've done for years, the first
little bit of self-sacrifice I've ever known, is really a sort of sin. I want to
be better. I am going to be better. Tell me something about yourself. What is
going on in town I've not been to the club for days.” “The people are still discussing
poor Basil’s disappearance.” “I should have thought that
they had got tired of that by this time,” said Dorian, pouring himself out some
wine and frowning slightly. “My dear boy, they have only been
talking about it for 6 weeks, and the British public are really not equal to
the mental strain of having more than one topic every 3 months. They have been
very fortunate lately, however. They have had my own divorce case and Alan
Campbell’s suicide. Now they have got the mysterious disappearance of an
artist. Scotland Yard still insists that the man in the greay olster who left for
Paris by the midnight train on the 9th of November was poor Basil, and the
French police declare that Basil never arrived in Paris at all. I suppose in
about a fortn T night we shall be told that he has been seen in San
Francisco. It is an odd thing, but everyone who disappears is said to be seen at San
Francisco. It must be a delightful city, and possess all the attractions of the next
world.” “What do you think has happened to Basil?” asked Dorian, holding up his
Burgundy against the light and wondering how it was that he could discuss the matter so
calmly. “I have not the slightest idea. If Basil chooses to hide in self it is no
business of mine. If he is dead, I don’t want to think about him. Death is the
only thing that ever terrifies me. I hate it.” “Why?” said the younger man
wearily. “Because,” said Lord Henry, passing beneath his nostrils the guilt trellis
of an open vinegret box, “one can survive everything nowaday except that. Death and
vulgarity are the only two facts in the 19th century that cannot explain a
way Let us have our coffee in the music room Dorian. You must play chopan to me.
The man with whom my wife ran away played chopan exquisitly Poor Victoria! I was very fond
of her. The house is rather lonely without her. Of course, married life is
merely a habit, a bad habit. But then one regrets the loss even of one’s worst
habits. Perhaps one regrets them the most.
They are such an essential part of one’s personality.” Dorian said nothing, but rose from the
table, and passing into the next room, sat down to the piano and let his fingers
stray across the white and black ivory of the keys. After the coffee had been brought
in, he stopped, and looking over at Lord Henry, said, “Harry, did it ever occur to
you that Basil was murdered?” Lord Henry yawned. “Basil was very popular, and always
wore a Waterbury watch. Why should could he have been murdered? He was not clever
enough to have enemies. Of course, he had a wonderful genius for painting. But a
man can paint like vasis and yet be as dull as possible. Basil was really rather
dull. He only interested me once, and that was when he told me, years ago, that he
had a wild adoration for you and that you were the dominant motive of his art.”
“I was very fond of Basil,” said Dorian with a note of sadness in his voice. “But
don’t people say that he was murder mured Oh, some of the papers do. It does
not seem to me to be at all probable. I know there are dreadful places in Paris,
but Basil was not the sort of man to have gone to them. He had no
curiosity. It was his chief defect.” “What would you say, Harry, if I
told you that I had murdered Basil?” said the younger man. He watched him intently
after he had spoken. “I would say, my dear fellow, that you were posing for a
character that doesn’t suit suot you. All crime is vulgar, just as all vulgarity is
crime. It is not in you, Dorian, to commit a murder I'm sorry if I hurt your vanity
by saying so, but I assure you it is true.
Crime belongs exclusively to the lower orders. I don’t blame them in the
smallest degree. I should fancy that crime was to them what art is to us,
simply a method of procuring extraordinary sensations.” “A method of procuring sensations?
Do you think, then, that a man who has once committed a murder could possibly
do the same crime again? Don’t tell me that.” “Oh! anything becomes a pleasure if one
does it too often,” cried Lord Henry, laughing. “That is one of the most
important secrets of life. I should fancy, however, that murder is always a mistake.
One should never do anything that one cannot talk about after dinner. But let
us pass from poor Basil. I wish I could believe that he had come to such a
really romantic end as you suggest, but I
can’t. I dare say he fell into the sa off an omnibus and that the conductor hushed
up the scandal. Yes: I should fancy that was his
end. I see him lying now on his back under those dull green waters, with the
heavy barges floating over him and long weeds catching in his hair. Do you know,
I don’t think he would have done much more good work. During the last 10 years
his painting had gone off very much.” Dorian heaved a sigh, and Lord Henry
strolled across the room and began to stroke the head of a curious Java parrot,
a large gray plumaged bird with pink crest and tail, that was balancing itself upon a bamboo
perch. As his pointed fingers touched it, it dropped the white scurf of crinkled
lids over black glass-like eyes and began to sway backwards and
forwards. “Yes,” he continued, turning around and taking his handkerchief out of his
pocket; “his painting had quite gone off.
It seemed to me to have lost something.
It had lost an ideal. When you and he ceased to be great
friends, he ceased to be a great artist.
What was it separated you? I suppose he bored you. If so, he never forgave you.
It’s a habit bores have. By the way, what has become of that wonderful portrait he
did of you? I don’t think I have ever seen it since he finished it. Oh! I
remember you're telling me years ago that you had sent it down to Selby, and
that it had got mislaid or stolen on the way. You never got it back? What a
pity! it was really a masterpiece. I remember I wanted to buy it. I wish I had
now. It belonged to Basil’s best period.
Since then, his work was that curious mixture of bad painting and good
intentions that always entitles a man to be called a representative British
artist. Did you advertise for it? You should.” “I forget,” said Dorian. “I suppose I
did. But I never really liked it. I am sorry I sat for it. The memory of the
thing is hateful to me. Why do you talk of it? It used to remind me of those
curious lines in some play— —Hamlet, I think— —how do they run?— “Like the painting
of a sorrow, A face without a heart.” Yes: that is what it was like.” Lord Henry
laughed. “If a man treats life artistically, his brain is his heart,” he
answered, sinking into an armchair Dorian Gray shook his head and
struck some soft chords on the piano.
“‘Like the painting of a sorrow,’” he repeated, “‘a face without a
heart.’” The elder man lay back and looked at him with half closed eyes.
“By the way, Dorian,” he said after a pause,
“‘what does it profit a man if he gain the whole world and lose— —how does the
quotation run?— ?—his own soul’?” The music jarred, and Dorian Gray started and stared at his
friend. “Why do you ask me that, Harry?” “My dear fellow,” said Lord Henry,
elevating his eyebrows in surprise, “I asked you because I thought
you might be able to give me an answer. That is all. I was going going
through the park last Sunday, and close by the Marble Arch there stood a little
crowd of shabby looking people listening to some vulgar Street Preacher As I
passed by, I heard the man yelling out that question to his audience. It struck
me as being rather dramatic. London is very rich in curious effects of that
kind. A wet Sunday, an UNC Christian in a Macintosh a ring of sickly white faces
under a broken roof of dripping umbrellas, and a wonderful fr pH flung
into the air by shrill hysterical lips— —it was really very good in its way, quite
a suggestion. I thought of telling the prophet that art had a soul, but that man
had not I'm afraid, however, he would not have understood
me.” “Don’t, Harry. The soul is a terrible reality. It can be bought, and sold, and
bed away. It can be poisoned, or made perfect. There is a soul in each one of
us. I know it.” “Do you feel quite sure of that, Dorian?” “Quite
sure.” “Ah! then it must be an illusion. The things one feels absolutely certain
about are never true. That is the fatality of faith, and the lesson of
romance. How grave you are! Don’t be so serious. What have you or I to do with
the superstitions of our age? No: we have given up our belief in the
soul. Play me something. Play me a nocturn Dorian, and, as you play, tell me, in a low
voice, how you have kept your youth. You must have some secret. I only 10 years
older than you are, and I'm wrinkled, and worn, and yellow. You are really wonderful,
Dorian. You have never looked more charming than you do tonight You remind
me of the day I saw you first. You were rather cheeky, very shy, and absolutely
extraordinary. You have changed, of course, but not in appearance. I wish you would tell me your
secret. To get back my youth I would do anything in the world, except take
exercise, get up early, or be respectable.
Youth! There is nothing like it. It’s absurd to talk of the ignorance
of youth. The only people to whose opinions I listen now with any respect
are people much younger than myself. They seem in front of me. Life has revealed to
them her latest wonder. As for the aged, I always contradict the aged. I do it on
principle. If you ask them their opinion on something that happened yesterday,
they solemnly give you the opinions current in 1820, when people wore high
stocks, believed in everything, and knew absolutely nothing. How lovely that thing
you are playing is! I wonder, did shop and write it at mayorca with the sea weeping
around the villa and the salt spray dashing against the pains It is
marvelously romantic. What a blessing it is that there is one art left to us that
is not imitative! Don’t stop. I want music tonight It seems to me that you are the
young Apollo and that I am marzia's listening to you. I have sorrows, Dorian, of my own, that
even you know nothing of. The tragedy of old age is not that
one is old, but that one is young. I am amazed sometimes at my own
sincerity. Ah, Dorian, how happy you are!
What an exquisite life you have had!
You have drunk deeply of everything. You have crushed the grapes against your
pallet Nothing has been hidden from you.
And it has all been to you no more than
the sound of music. It has not marred you.
You are still the same.” “I am not the same,
Harry.” “Yes, you are the same. I wonder what the rest of your life will be. Don’t
spoil it by renunciations. At present you are a perfect type. Don’t make yourself
incomplete. You are quite flawless now.
You need not shake your head: you know you are. Besides, Dorian, don’t deceive
yourself. Life is not governed by will or intention. Life is a question of nerves,
and fibers and slowly built up cells in which thought hides itself and passion has its
dreams. You may fancy yourself safe and think yourself strong. But a chanon of
color in a room or a morning sky, a particular perfume that you had once
loved and that brings subtle memories with it, a line from a forgotten poem
that you had come across again, a cadence from a piece of music that you had
ceased to play— —I tell you, Dorian, that it is on things like these that our lives
depend. Browning writes about that somewhere; but our own senses will imagine them for
us. There are moments when the odor of Leela blanc passes suddenly across me,
and I have to live the strangest month of my life over
again. I wish I could change places with you, Dorian. The world has cried out
against us both, but it has always worshiped you. It always will worship you.
You are the type of what the age is searching for, and what it is afraid it has
found I'm so glad that you have never done anything, never carved a statue, or
painted a picture, or produced anything outside of yourself! Life has been your
art. You have set yourself to music. Your days are your sonnets.” Dorian rose up from the piano
and passed his hand through his hair. “Yes, life has been exquisite,” he
murmured, “but I'm not going to have the same life, Harry. And you must not say
these extravagant things to me. You don’t know everything about me. I think that if
you did, even you would turn from me. You laugh. Don’t laugh.” “Why have you stopped playing,
Dorian?
Go back and give me the nocturn over again. Look at that great honey colored
moon that hangs in the dusky air she's waiting for you to charm her, and if you
play she will come closer to the earth.
You won’t? Let us go to the club, then. It has
been a charming evening, and we must end it charmingly. There is someone at Whit's
who wants immensely to know you— —young Lord P Bournemouth’s eldest son he's
already copied your neck ties and has begged me to introduce him to you. He is
quite delightful and rather reminds me of you.” “I hope not,” said Dorian with a sad
look in his eyes. “But I am tired tonight
Harry. I sh go to the club. It is nearly
11: and I want to go to bed early.” “Do stay. You have never played so well as
tonight There was something in your touch that was wonderful. It had more
expression than I had ever heard from it before.” “It is because I am going to be
good,” he answered, smiling. “I am a little changed already.”
“You cannot change to me, Dorian,” said Lord Henry. “You and I will always be friends.”
“Yet you poisoned me with a book once. I should not forgive that. Harry, promise me
that you will never lend that book to anyone It does harm.” “My dear boy, you are really
beginning to moralize. You will soon be going about like the converted, and the
revivalist, warning people against all the sins of which you have grown tired.
You are much too delightful to do that.
Besides, it is no use. You and I are what we are, and will be what we will
be. As for being poisoned by a book, there is no such thing as that. Art has no
influence upon action. It annihilates the desire to act. It is superbly sterile. The
books that the world calls immoral are books that show the world its own shame.
That is all. But we won’t discuss literature. Come around tomorrow I'm going to ride at
11: We might go together, and I will take you to lunch afterwards with Lady branom
She is a charming woman, and wants to consult you about some tapestries she's
thinking of buying. Mind you come. Or shall we lunch with our little duchess?
She says she never sees you now. Perhaps you are tired of Gladis I thought you would be.
Her clever tongue gets on one’s nerves.
Well, in any case, be here at 11: Must I really come,
Harry?” “Certainly. The park is quite lovely now. I don’t think there have been such
lilacs since the year I met you.” “Very well. I shall be here at 11: said Dorian.
“Good night, Harry.” As he reached the door, he hesitated for a moment, as if he had
something more to say. Then he sighed and went out out dsh chapter